Finding Aid for the George M. Britton Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
George M. Britton Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0052
.42 linear_feet
Biography/History
George Mellinger Britton [1947 - ] received a B.A. degree in 1969 in Political Science from Vanderbilt University. His wife, Shelley Guilford Roberts Britton also attended Vanderbilt. He became a broker in Houston, Texas, collecting rare manuscripts and maps. He has also donated materials, relative to the Early Republic of Texas to Rice University, University of Houston, and the University of Texas.
The collection is comprised of four parts: first, documents of the Republic of Texas, 1837-1845; second, the early documents of Tennessee, 1817-1862; third, Senate and House broadsides from 1835-1848, and finally scrapbooks relative to the American Civil War, 1860-1865.
Scope and Contents
This .42 linear feet collection is divided into four series:
Series I contains documents related of the Republic of Texas. These include writs, petitions, and briefs from 1837-1845 regarding persons originally from the State of Tennessee who played a key role in Texas history. The files are alphabetical.
Series II contains pamphlets relating to the history of Tennessee from 1817-1862. Topics are varied by include: vacant lands, presidential candidates, party organizations, tariffs, government expenditures, and foreign relations. The files are chronological.
Series III contains original United States Senate and U.S. House of Representatives broadsides from the 24th through the 30th Congresses in Washington, D.C., relating to the state of Tennessee, from 1835-1848. The Bills cover increases in pensions, invalid pension rolls, payment for horses, establishment of a Marine Hospital at Memphis, and work on the Cumberland Road. The files are chronological.
Series IV contains letters, speeches, circulars, broadsides, monographs, reports, and bills relating to the American Civil War, 1860-1865. The collection was originally assembled as two scrapbooks, on self-adhesive pages but with a backing for each item. The two scrapbooks chronicle the Civil War from beginning to end. The original order of materials has been maintained.
The collection was donated to Special Collections, during the 1980s by Mr. and Mrs. George M. Britton.
- Series I - Republic of Texas
  - Anderson, Kenneth L., Tennessee jurist who immigrated to Texas in 1829. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    June Term 1842. Petition on behalf of Burwell J. Thompson to the Probate Court, filing three part protest to the appointment of John C. Brook as Administrator of the estate of Ephraim Talley. Signed by Anderson as attorney. Anderson was District Attorney of the Fifth Texas Judicial District in 1843 and Vice-President of the Republic in 1844.
  - Chance, Joseph L., Texas jurist born in Tennessee July 4, 1800. Washington County. September 25, 1837. Petition for letters of Administration for Estates of Ewing and Young Caruthers who fell "in the massacre of Mayor Ward's Battalion in the spring of 1836." A delegate to the 1833 Convention, Chance was a Captain of Texas Volunteers during the Texas Revolution. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dyer, Clement C., Texas jurist and magistrate born in Dyersburg, Tennessee, January 29, 1800. Fort Bend County, April 4, 1845. Signed as Chief Justice certifying interrogations in the case of Noah Woods vs Harriet Canfield. Dyer, one of the original OLD 300 Colonist of Texas and pioneer Fort Bend settler, was justice of the Supreme Court of the Republic. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gant, William W., Texas jurist born in Tennessee in January 1809. Washington, Texas, February 1840. Signed as attorney. Receipt to Shubal Marsh for legal fee for writing petition for "prolongation of time." Gant fought at San Jacinto and served in the 1st, 2nd, and 4th Congresses. He was killed by Indians in 1840 and the first memorial of the Texas Bar was published in his honor. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Heard, William Jones Elliot, Texas jurist and legislator born in Knoxville, Tennessee on August 16, 1801. Colorado County, September 24, 1838. Signed as Judge of Probate. Appointment of Basil Illiams as Administrator of the Estate of Robert Cunningham. Heard, a captain at the Battle of San Jacinto, was Chief Justice of Wharton County in 1839. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Houston, Samuel, Texas political and military leader, Governor of Tennessee. April 28, 1838. Texas Revolution claim document, payment of which is declined by Houston whilst President of the Republic. Houston served as President, Senator and Governor of Texas and let the Texan victory against Santa Ana at the Battle of San Jacinto. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mayfield, James S., attorney and legislator born in Tennessee in 1809. Fayette County, September 29, 1845. Signed Mayfield and Crutcher, attorneys. Petition for James Callison, auditor for the estate of Jasper A. Sargeant. Mayfield served in the 5th and 6th Republic of Texas Congresses and introduced the Franco-Texienne Bill. He was secretary of State under President Lamar. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oldham, Williamson Simpson, Arkansas jurist and legislator born in Franklin County, Tennessee on July 19, 1813. Washington County, July 1842. Petition, as executor for extension of time in settling the Estate of James Bowie, who was killed in the Alamo. Oldham, a fire brand secessionist and enemy of Sam Houston, represented Texas in the Confederate Congress. In 1859 he published "A Digest of the General Statute Laws of the State of Texas." (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reed, Henry, Texas jurist born in Tennessee on November 10, 1800. Franklin, April 24, 1845. Signed as Chief Justice. Interrogations in the case of Barron vs Hill regarding mortgaged slaves. Reed fought in the Battle of San Jacinto and was first Chief Justice of Robertson County. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Roddy, Ephraim, Texas jurist and magistrate born in Tennessee in 1793. Washington, July 23, 1838. Signed as attorney for McKinney and Williams in suit against D. P. Woodlief, for default on note, Roddy was a delegate to the convention of 1833 and was first Magistrate of Washington, after annexation. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Scurry, Richardson, A., Texas jurist and legislator born at Gallatin, Tennessee on November 11, 1811. Montgomery, November 29, 1840, Character witness for Pleasant Gray accepted as evidence in suit. Scurry, a brilliant attorney, fought in the Battle of San Jacinto, was District Attorney of the 5th Judicial District, Judge of the 6th District and a member of the Supreme Court. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Terrell, George W., Texas jurist who served as Attorney General under Tennessee Governor Sam Houston. May 14, 1844. Authentication of signature of Samuel Nelson in the case of Nelson vs Nelson. Terrell, a friend of Sam Houston was Attorney General in Tennessee when Houston was Governor. Migrating to Texas he was District Attorney of San Augustine in 1837, and later Attorney General of the Republic of Texas. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II - Pamphlets
  - Tennessee. Report of the select committee appointed on the 20th instant, on a memorial of the legislature of North Carolina, remonstrating against the act of Congress, passed in the year 1806, "authorizing the State of Tennessee to issue grants and perfect titles to certain lands therein described, and to settle the claims to the vacant and unappropriated lands within the same." North Carolina, January 28, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tennessee. Speeches of Mr. White of Tennessee, delivered in the Senate of the U.S., June 1832 on the Bill to re-charter the Bank of the United States. Washington (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tennessee. Disposal of Vacant Lands. Memorial of the General Assembly of the State of Tennessee, in relation to the disposal of vacant Lands. Washington, April 9, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tennessee. Letter of the Hon. Hugh L. White to the Legislature of Tennessee on declining to obey certain of their Resolutions of Instruction, and Resigning the Office of Senator of the United States. Washington 1840. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tennessee. The Governor's Message: Delivered in the House of Representatives on the 3rd October, 1843. Nashville (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Mr. M. P. Gentry, of Tennessee on the Tariff delivered in the House of Representatives of the U.S., July 2, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tennessee. Report: The Committee on Public Lands, to whom was referred the "memorial of the General Assembly of the State of Tennessee, asking a cession and relinquishment of the lands south and west of the congressional reservation line, and an appropriation in behalf of the West Tennessee College, at Jackson," according to order, have had the same under consideration, and respectfully report: Washington, January 27, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. H. L. Turney, of Tennessee on the Tennessee Resolutions delivered in the Senate of the United States, February 18, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. George W. Jones, of Tennessee on the Bill to provide for the better Organization of the Treasury and for the collection, safe-keeping, transfer, and disbursement of the Public Revenue. Washington (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Mr. Stanton, of Tennessee on the Smithsonian Bill delivered in the House of Representatives, April 22, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. L. B. Chase, of Tennessee on the Tariff delivered in the House of Representatives, June 26, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Mr. Ewing, of Tennessee on the Tariff delivered in the House of Representatives, June 27, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. M. P. Gentry, of Tennessee on Presidential Candidates, Party Organizations delivered in the House of Representatives, June 14, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. John H. Savage, of Tennessee on the Old Soldiers' Pension Bill; delivered in the House of Representatives, December 16, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. J. D. C. Atkins, of Tennessee, on the Position and Tendency of Parties delivered in the House of Representatives, January 24, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. William T. Avery, of Tennessee, on Our Foreign Relations delivered in the House of Representatives, January 24, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. Samuel A. Smith, of Tennessee, on Government Expenditures; delivered in the House of Representatives, January 31, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Mr. Grundy, of Tennessee, on Mr. Foot's Resolution, proposing an inquiry into the expediency of abolishing The office of Surveyor General of Public Lands, and discontinuing Further surveys delivered in the Senate of the United States, February 29, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. W. B. Stokes, of Tennessee, on the Election of Speaker, delivered in the House of Representatives, January 7, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Tennessee. The Constitutionality and Rightfulness of Secession. Speech of Hon. Andrew Johnson, of Tennessee, in the Senate of the United States, December 18 and 19, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Tennessee. Corruptions in the Navy Department. Speech of Hon. Robert Hatton, of Tennessee in the House of Representatives, June 13, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Tennessee. Let Us Remain One People! An Appeal to the North. Speech of Hon. Horace Maynard, of Tennessee, in the House of Representatives, February 6, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. Andrew Johnson, of Tennessee, on the State of the Union; delivered in the Senate of the United States, February 5 and 6, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Tennessee. Speech of Hon. Horace Maynard, of Tennessee, of the Claim of Joseph Segar to a Seat in the House; delivered in the House of Representatives, February 11, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tennessee. Impeachment of West H. Humphreys, Judge of the United Stated District Court of Tennessee, March 4, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series III - House and Senate Broadsides
  - United States Senate, Washington, D.C., S. 9. A Bill for the Relief of John McCartney of Tennessee for cattle taken by "troops in the service of the United States.", December 21, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 960. A Bill for the Relief of Isaac Justis, of Tennessee, placed on the roll of invalid pensioners by the Secretary of War., January 2, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 953. A Bill for the benefit of Thomas Collins of the State of Tennessee, placed on the roll of invalid pensioners by the Secretary of war., January 2, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 966. A Bill for the Relief of William Smith, of Lincoln County, Tennessee, placed on the roll of revolutionary pensioners by the Secretary., January 2, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 1086. A Bill extending the provisions of the act entitled "An Act to Amend an Act Entitled" An act to provide for payment of Horses lost or destroyed in the military service of the United States.", January 26, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 1156. A Bill granting a pension to Randolph Carter of the State of Tennessee, placed on the roll of invalid pensioners by the Secretary of War., February 16, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 485. A Bill for the benefit of Arthur R. Frogge of Fentress County, Tennessee placed on the invalid pension roll by the Secretary of War., December 31, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 558. A Bill for the Benefit of Joseph Craigmiles, of the State of Tennessee, placed on the invalid pensioner's roll by the Secretary of War., January 28, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 555. A Bill to pay Captain John B. Croner;s Company of Mounted Volunteers, Tennessee Militia., January 28, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - United States Senate, Washington, D.C., S. 129. A Bill for the relief of General John Cocke of Tennessee., February 13, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 625. A Bill granting a pension to James Davidson of Fentress County, Tennessee placed on the roll of invalid pensioners by the Secretary of War., February 15, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 45. A Bill for the relief of Joseph M. Rhea, of the County of Sullivan, in the State of Tennessee placed on the roll of invalid pensioners by the Secretary of War., January 8, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 500. A Bill for the establishment of a Marine Hospital at Memphis., July 13, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - United States Senate, Washington, D.C., S. 138. A Bill for the relief of General Robert Armstrong., February 12, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 230. A Bill to increase the pension of Henry Click of Cocke County, Tennessee., February 21, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 244. A Bill for the relief of Daniel Steenrod of Tennessee for extra work on the Cumberland Road., February 29, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - U. S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., H.R. 478. A Bill for the relief of Archibald Beard, and twenty-one Other Tennessee Mounted Volunteers., May 16, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series IV - Scrapbooks
  - Deconstructed Scrapbook #1
    - Confederate Battlefield Broadside - tinted (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Address to the Anti-Slavery Christians of the United States Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Slave Approaching Abraham Lincoln Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - An Examination of the Mosaic Laws of Servitude Pamphlet - by William Jay (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Statue of Abraham Lincoln Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Is Slavery Sanctioned By The Bible? Pamphlet - by Isaac Allen (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - A Sumter Casemate During the Bombardment: Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Extracts From The American Slave Code Pamphlet - No.1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jefferson Davis Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Reply of Hon. Jefferson Davis, of Mississippi, to the Speech of Senator Douglas, in the U. S. Senate, May 16 and 17, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Fatal Wounding of Stonewall Jackson Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Speech of Hon Robert Toombs on "The Crisis" Delivered Before the Georgia Legislature, December 7, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Panic of the Union Troops at Bull Run Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - An Ordinance - Providing for the Election of Electors of President and Vice President of the Confederate States - Broadside (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Rock of Chickamauga Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ayer's American Almanac Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Death of Albert Sidney Johnston Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter to Hon Reverdy Johnson on the Proceeding at the Meeting, held at Maryland Institute, January 10, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Robert E. Lee Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Adjutant and Inspector General's Office - Richmond General Orders No. 3, February 6, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pickett's Charge at Gettysburg Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Circular Instruction, No. 2 Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department, March 8, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Robert E. Lee Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Circular Instruction, No. 1 Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department, March 6, 1861. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Soldiers in Battle Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Treasury Circular, No. 6 Memminger, C. G., Secretary of the Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department Montgomery, April 5, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Group of Confederate Prisoners being Marched to the Rear Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Treasury Circular, No. 7 Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department Montgomery, April 5, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Richmond and Vicinity Broadside - map - black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Treasury Circular, No. 8 Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department, April 10, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Deconstructed Scrapbook #2
    - Confederate Soldiers Broadside - tinted, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Treasury Department Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Richmond During the Evacuation Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Treasury Circular, No. 10 Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department Richmond, June 7, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Confederate and Union Soldiers Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Treasury Circular, No. 11 Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department Richmond, August 8, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grant's Attack on Fort Donelson Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Treasury Circular, No. 12 Mimminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate States of America, Treasury Department Richmond, September 21, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - W. T. Sherman Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Causes of the American Civil War Pamphlet - by John Lothrop Motley (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Cavalry Fight at Brandy Station Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Treasury Circular Memminger, C. G., Secretary of Treasury Confederate State of America, Treasury Department, February 6, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Grant Reconnoitering in the Rain at Belmont Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The War: Its Cause and Cure Speech of Hon. William M. Davis, of Penn., In the House of Representatives, March 6, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Battle of Atlanta Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Rebellion: Its Origin, and the Means of Suppressing It Speech of Hon. Jno. T. Nixon, of New Jersey In the House of Representatives, April 11, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grant's Arrival on the Battlefield Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Future Civilization of the South Sermon by Edward E. Hale South Congregational Church, Boston, April 18, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Capture of Jefferson Davis Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Confiscation of Rebel Property Speech of Hon. W. P. Cutler, of Ohio In the House of Representatives, April 23, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Robert E. Lee Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - House Bill No. 9 House of Representatives, May 3, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Major-General Benjamin F. Butler and Staff Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Returned Prisoners 38th Congress, 1st Session, Report No. 67 House of Representatives, May 9, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Union Soldiers in Battle Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - House Bill No. 214 House of Representatives, November 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "No Terms Except Unconditional Surrender" Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Enlistment of Rebel Prisoners 38th Congress, 2nd Session, Ex. Doc. No. 80 House of Representatives, February 25, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Robert E. Lee Signing Document Broadside - black and white (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Robert E. Lee: A Character Sketch Pamphlet, by H. H. Smith, May 20, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)